Guide to the Few Federation records, 1973-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Few Federation records 1973-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Few Federation.
1 linear feet Extent: 1000 Items
Few Federation, an undergraduate organization which united House A, Cleland, Sigma Alpha Epsilon, and Bunch of Guys Houses on Duke University's west campus, from 1971 to the early 1980s. Collection includes agendas, minutes, constitutions, calendars, reports, correspondence, fliers, newsletters, logo sketches, and printed matter. Major subjects include student life at Duke University, dormitories, residence and education, college freshmen, Cleland House, House A, Bunch of Guys, and Sigma Alpha Epsilon Houses. Materials range in date from 1973-1982.]
RL.01559
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Few Federation records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1976, 1988.
Historical Note
Few Federation, an undergraduate organization which united House A, Cleland, Sigma Alpha Epsilon, and Bunch of Guys Houses on Duke University's west campus, from 1971 to the early 1980s. The Few Federation hosted recreational and credit-earning courses on a variety of topics including auto mechanics, needlepoint, electronic music and leadership. Social events hosted by the Few Federation included concerts, backgammon tournaments, and computer dating parties. New residents of houses in Few Federation were partnered with returning students. This Freshman Advisory Council was widely successful in orienting them to the Duke University and campus life.
Three other Federations existed on campus around from the early 1970s to the early 1980s: the Edens, Baldwin, and Kilgo Federations. These independent living groups, centered around several of the quadrangles on East and West campuses, banded together to form college-type communities within the university setting. Faculty endorsed federations for their potential to help students realize their personal educational goals. Students supported federations because they provided a wider base for friendships and a variety of opportunities for involvement. A federation supplemented the on-campus living experience with a variety of house courses, occasional educational programs, festivals, dances, and parties. Each federation was headed by faculty who were responsible for organizing new programs, guiding governance of the federation structure, and facilitating partnerships among living groups.
In the early 1980s, federations were abolished in order to improve balance between men and women, and between selective and independent living groups on campus. While individual living groups were chartered and occasionally dissolved, the system of selective living, within the parameters of a program of residential living groups within residence halls, remained intact.
Collection Overview
Contains materials pertaining to the Few Federation, an undergraduate organization which united House A, Cleland, Sigma Alpha Epsilon, and Bunch of Guys Houses on Duke University's west campus, from 1971 to the early 1980s. Materials range in date from 1973-1982.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
College freshmen -- North Carolina -- Durham; College students -- Housing; Dormitories -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Few Federation; Residence and education; Sigma Alpha Epsilon. North Carolina Nu chapter; Student housing -- North Carolina -- Durham
Related Material
Alspaugh House records
Duke University Archives
Arts and Sciences Council. Residential Life Committee records
Duke University Archives
Association of Independent Houses records
Duke University Archives
Baldwin Federation records
Duke University Archives
Bassett House records
Duke University Archives
Brown House records
Duke University Archives
Bunch of Guys records, 1960-1972
Duke University Archives
Fraternities and Sororities Collection
Duke University Archives
Gilbert-Addoms Residence Hall records
Duke University Archives
Giles House records
Duke University Archives
Jarvis House records
Duke University Archives
Living Groups collection
Duke University Archives
Mirecourt House records
Duke University Archives
Pegram House records
Duke University Archives
S.H.A.R.E. records
Duke University Archives
Warwick House records
Duke University Archives
York House records
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Few Federation history, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Few Federation constitution, 1979
  - Agendas, 1977-1981
  - Minutes, 1977-1981
  - Financial materials, 1978-1980
  - Correspondence, 1979-1980
  - Elected officers lists, 1977-1981
  - Election materials, 1979-1982
  - Freshman Advisory Counselors, general program materials, 1978-1981
  - Freshman Advisory Counselors, program evaluations, circa 1978
  - Faculty advising in Few Federation houses, circa 1977-1979
  - Academics and Faculty Relations Committee notes and announcements, circa 1979
  - Faculty fellows and faculty associates correspondence, circa 1978-1981
  - Calendars, circa 1981
  - Event planning materials, requests for funds and notes, circa 1980-1982
  - Event fliers and notices, circa 1977-1982
  - House courses, lists of courses offered, 1975-1981
  - House courses, course materials and syllabi, 1977-1978
  - House courses, course materials and syllabi, 1979
  - House courses, course materials and syllabi, 1980-1981
  - House courses, evaluations and papers, circa 1977-1980
  - Few Federation logo contest sketches, circa 1980
  - Lounge furniture and decoration issues, 1977-1980
  - Vending machine issues, 1980
  - Newsletter of the Few Federation and Few Notes, 1974-1981
  - A Proposal to Adopt the Federation Model as the Paradigm for the Duke University Residential System, 1979
  - Federations in 1978-1979: A Series of Reports, 1979 and Report of the Coordinator of Federations, 1979-1980, 1980